Thank you very much. So, first, let me begin by apologizing. Juan asked me to give this
talk specifically to give a talk which was directed at an audience of physicists. And
as I was preparing this talk, I realized that I don't really know how to do that. So I'm
going to give a talk which is really the same talk that I would give to an audience of mathematicians.
You should feel free to interrupt me if I'm not making sense.
I'd like to begin with a little bit of history. And I noticed that in the second row here,
we have one of the principal actors in the story that I'm going to be telling.
If I get the history a little bit wrong, feel free to correct it.
So the story I want to start with is in the late 80s, with the question that Natia asked about
the Jones polynomial. So the Jones polynomial is an invariant of a knot, and it was constructed
by Vaughan Jones, and his construction made use of a particular way that you could represent a knot.
You can always represent a knot in three-dimensional space by drawing a
braid and then closing up the ends. So he gave a construction which made use of a braid,
and then checked that this was independent of the particular representation that he chose.
And Natia asked if this was actually necessary, or if there was some construction that you could
give that was intrinsically three-dimensional, that really just used a knot in three-dimensional space
and extracted this invariant, the Jones polynomial. So this was answered by Witten,
who introduced something called quantum Chern-Simons theory. So quantum Chern-Simons theory
is an example of a topological quantum field theory, and it comes to you with a huge number
of interrelated invariants that you can try to compute. And what Witten showed is that if you
choose a couple of very simple examples of things that you could try to compute,
what would pop out is values of the Jones polynomial evaluated at roots of unity.
So that gave a sort of physical interpretation of what the Jones polynomial is, and also suggested
that the theory of the Jones polynomial is really just a small fragment of some much larger story
that people got very excited about. So in particular, Atiyah got excited about it,
and motivated by this and several other examples, made an attempt to communicate back to mathematicians
what this elaborate structure was about. Now that definition is where I want to begin the story.
So this is Atiyah's
definition of what a topological quantum field theory is. So fix a dimension D,
and describe what I'll call a TQFT in dimension D. Maybe some people would say it's in dimension
D minus one plus one. So a TQFT is a rule, which does the following.
Maybe let me give this a name. The rule is Z. So to every closed D minus one manifold,
you assign Z of M, which is a complex vector space.
And to every bordism, D minus one manifold. So bordism, let me remind you,
here's a picture of a bordism. A bordism means a D manifold whose boundary, which has boundary,
and whose boundary is divided into two pieces, an incoming piece and an outgoing piece.
So I'll write B for the bordism, and to say that it's
a bordism is to say that the boundary of B
is written as a disjoint union of two pieces M and N. And here by this bar,
I'll mean that I'm giving M the opposite orientation. And you assign a little right as Z of B.
It's a map from Z of M to Z of M, which is a complex linear.
So this is, first of all, subject to a couple of rules for what happens when you glue bordisms.
So first of all, if I take Z of M cross the interval zero one,
that's something that you can think of as a bordism from the manifold M to itself.
And this is supposed to be the identity map.
Vector space Z of M to Z of N. And if you have two bordisms, let's say,
say you have manifolds M0, M1, and M2 of dimension D minus one.
Let's draw them as if they're one dimensional. And then suppose that you have bordisms from
bordism from M0 to M1 and a bordism from M1 to M2 as drawn in this picture.
Well, then you can glue them together along this common copy of M1 and make a bordism from
M0 to M2. Let me call this B and B prime. And in this situation,
the linear map that you're supposed to assign to this glued together object
is supposed to be the composition of the two linear maps associated to the individual constituents.
And finally, there's a rule that says that when you decompose something as a disjoint union,
then you're supposed to take tensor products of the corresponding vector spaces.
So if I take a disjoint union of finitely many compact manifolds of dimension D minus one,
this invariant is supposed to be identified with the tensor product of the individual constituents.
A sort of degenerate case of that is if this is the empty collection of manifolds.
So what Z is supposed to assign to the empty manifold is the tensor product of the empty
collection of vector spaces, which by convention is the complex numbers.
And well, there are some additional axioms that I should write down about how these isomorphisms
behave. First, they should be compatible with these linear maps and they should be suitably
behave well with respect to permuting the factors and so forth. I'll leave those to your imagination.
So this was a T as definition.
Now you can summarize this definition very efficiently in the language of category theory.
So let me, if you fix a dimension D, there's a category which I'll denote by
Cob D. So this is the category whose objects are closed D minus one manifolds.
And morphisms are given by orders of D minus one.
Morphism from, for example, two circles to one circle is a picture like this.
And let's say we consider two morphisms to be the same
if the total spaces of the orders are diffeomorphic.
And so, a efficient way of stating this is that the definition
of T is a tensor factor from this category Cob D to the category of complex vector spaces.
Saying that it's a functor is everything that I said up to this point.
And saying that it's a tensor functor, well, it means that it preserves tensor products where
on the left-hand side what tensor product means is disjoint union.
So it takes disjoint unions of manifolds to tensor products of complex vectors.
I have a question. So, yeah, think about the category.
So these morphisms, are they supposed to be maps? They're supposed to be
here? Sorry, in this category? Yeah. Well, the morphisms in this category are
bordisms. So here's a, in Cob two, this is. Yeah. I guess my question is,
morphism sounds like it's some kind of map between one thing and another.
Right. But here is just some space that joins the two. There is no sense in.
I mean, I guess in most, most times that you give an example of a category, the morphisms in that
category are something that you can think of as maps that preserve some structure.
But this is an example of a category, which, you know, a priori you don't think about that.
Category just means there's some composition law, which is associative,
and that's true of this gluing law for board systems.
So maybe a remark that I should make at this point, that this has many variants.
Depending on what kind of manifold you want to be talking about. So I have been implicitly so far,
and will continue implicitly in this lecture, to assume that when I say manifold, I mean a manifold
to assume that when I say manifold, I mean a manifold with an orientation and no additional
structure. But you could have other conventions. So you could consider.
So you could consider unoriented manifolds.
So
unoriented manifolds, you can consider oriented manifolds, you can consider spin manifolds.
And which variant that you want to consider would depend on which particular example that
you wanted to get. So, for example, if you were interested in quantum churn simons theory,
then oriented manifold is not quite enough to have these invariants. You need some additional
structure like a framing or a P1 structure in order to make the invariants that you're interested in
in order to make the invariants that you're interested in unambiguous.
So I'm going to stick for most of this lecture to talking just about oriented manifolds,
although the fact that there are many variants is going to come up at the very end,
assuming that we get there.
Okay, so just to get us all on the same page, I want to do the example.
Okay, so let's try to understand the structure that we see when we have one of these rules.
Well, first and foremost, we have to assign a vector space to every closed manifold of dimension
one. Now closed manifolds of dimension one are very easy to classify. A connected closed
manifold of dimension one is a circle and a general closed manifold of dimension one is
just a disjoint union of finitely many circles. So if you have one of these TQFTs, you could
evaluate it on the circle and you would get some complex vector space, which I'll denote by A.
And once you know what you just want to assign to the circle, you know what you want to assign
to any closed manifold of dimension one. For example, those who took three circles,
well because Z is supposed to send disjoint unions to tensor products,
this would just assign a tensor product of three copies of A.
Of course, you're not done at this point, because in order to define a vector, you have to say not
just what it does on the objects, but also what it does on the morphism. What it does to board
between manifolds of dimension one.
So there's a particularly interesting picture that you can draw,
which I've already drawn once and I'll draw again, is this manifold with boundary called
a pair of pants. You can regard it as a bordism from two circles to a single circle. And if you
evaluate Z on this, you'll get something which I'll call M. It's a linear map from A times A
into A. Let me just remark that the axioms imply that M is commutative and associative.
I chose the letter A because this thing is going to end up having the structure of an algebra.
There's also a unit for this multiplication. So you can evaluate Z on a disk, and I'm going
to think of the disk as it's a manifold whose boundary is a circle. I'm going to think of
that circle as outgoing. So this disk is a bordism from the empty manifold to the circle.
That gives you a linear map from Z of the empty manifold to Z of the circle. And Z of the empty
manifold, remember, is the complex numbers and Z of the circle is A. So this you can just think
of as an element of A, and this element is the unit. Yes, you identify a linear map with
an element of A by evaluating it at the element one. So this is the unit for the multiplication
of A.
Also think of the circle, or sorry, the disk as a bordism in the other direction. You can regard
that boundary circle as an incoming circle rather than an outgoing circle. If you evaluate Z on the
disk drawn this other way, this gives you instead a map from A to the complex numbers. I'll write
this as TR for trace. And so a rule of thumb that someone once gave me for a math talk
is that every talk should have at least one proof in it. I'm going to apply this rule here.
I'm going to prove this one thing because it's kind of going to come up several times in this
lecture. So lemma that this trace map gives non-degenerate pairing.
So if I look at A, tensor A, mapping to A by multiplication and then mapping to the complex
numbers by other trace. So this is a bilinear form on A. This gives an isomorphism
from A to its dual.
And let me just remark as an aside, this implies that A has to be finite dimension.
When I say dual here, I mean dual in the purely algebraic sense. And so if A was an infinite
dimensional vector space, its dual space would be an even bigger infinite dimensional vector space.
So what's the proof of this? So this linear map from A tensor A to the complex numbers,
it's what Z assigns to a particular picture in which the multiplication is associated to
this picture. And then if I want to compose that with the trace, I just cap it off on the other end
with a disk. In other words, I'm looking at Z of a cylinder, but I'm thinking of the cylinder
as having two incoming circles. Of course there's another picture I could draw
with this. I could think of that same cylinder
pointed the other way. I can imagine that there's a cylinder with two outgoing circles.
So this gives me a map from the complex numbers into A tensor A. And this in particular
gives you a linear map from the dual of A back into A.
So this bilinear form I could think of as a map F from A to its dual. This construction gives you
a map from the dual of A back into A. And my claim is that these maps are actually inverses of one
another. The claim F composed with G is the identity map from A to itself.
And the proof is a proof by picture is that F composed with G is something that you can
get as Z evaluated on a particular shape. Namely, you would take Z and you would evaluate it
on the picture that you get by
drawing this and attaching it to this and thinking of that thing as a bordism
from one circle to itself. And then
let me observe that this is the same as Z evaluated on the straight cylinder.
This is a diffeomorphism in direct.
So actually, we wanted more slowly for how this is, which of the two pieces are F and G in the
picture. Right. So I have a map from A to, so how is F constructed? F was constructed essentially by
using this cylinder, this piece here, and evaluating Z on it, I'm getting a map from A tensor A to the
complex numbers. And similarly, G was obtained by evaluating F there. G was obtained by evaluating
Z on this cylinder here, bordism from the empty set to two circles. And, well, that's an element
of A tensor A. So if A is finite dimensional, that's the same thing as a map like this,
but in general it gives you a map like this. And the claim is that if you unwind the definitions
of what it means to now compose F with G, that it's going to be given by
stacking the pictures next to each other just like this.
Let me leave this as an exercise to think through.
So, actually, and let me just note, we've proven something that's true in general,
and that we're going to use again later. So in any dimension,
so nothing that I, the definition that I've given involves complex conjugation on the
complex numbers. I could have replaced the complex numbers by any vector space.
Yeah, so this dual means not the permission dual, it means the linear dual.
Okay, so in any dimension, the same argument
shows that if you evaluate z on some manifold and give it the opposite orientation,
that this is, can be identified with the dual space of z evaluated on manifold M itself,
and both are finite dimensional.
Okay, so let's go back to dimension two. So ATIA's axioms tell you you have this vector space A,
it has a commutative and associative multiplication, and it has this trace map,
which gives you a non-degenerate pairing. So that structure has a name, so you get
A, or let's say A is what's called a commutative for Bain-Eccentra.
So this term just means all the structure that we just saw. It's a vector space with a
multiplication, which is commutative, associative, and unital,
and a trace map, which is non-degenerate in this sense.
And I don't know who to attribute this to, I think it's a folk theorem,
is that the converse is true.
It's also true, namely, any near-diffruminous algebra
extended, or let's say comes about in this way.
The data of a two-dimensional TQFT in the sense of ATIA's definition is exactly the same as the
data of this particular algebraic structure. So here we analyzed TQFTs in dimension two by
emphasizing the value that they take on a manifold of dimension one. In this case,
the only manifold, interesting manifold, to consider is the circle.
But another point of view that you could take is that what's interesting is instead to emphasize
what these invariants do on manifolds of the highest dimension. So let's return
in the case of the general TQFT in any dimension
if M is a closed manifold,
in dimension D,
we view it
as a boredism
from the empty manifold to itself.
So if we have one of these TQFTs, we're allowed to evaluate it on M,
and we get a linear map from Z of the empty manifold as you get the empty manifold.
This is just the complex numbers, this is the complex numbers, and this map is just given by
multiplications of the two-dimensional TQFTs. So this is a linear map of the two-dimensional
TQFTs. This is just given by multiplication by a particular scalar, and I'll abuse notation by
just calling that scalar Z of it. So one point of view is that first and foremost,
the TQFT on Z is an invariant
of the two-dimensional TQFTs.
Sorry, so thus far you've been using consistently M as a notation for D minus
one dimensions and B for the D dimensions.
Yeah, if you want, we just change that.
Same, same story.
Okay.
So if you believe this folk theorem here, it's telling you that in particular if you
have a commutative for baneous algebra, then you can extract from it an invariant of closed two
manifolds.
The folk theorem says
a is a commutative for baneous algebra
that comes from a TQFTZ, and then I can evaluate Z on a surface sigma, and I get some number.
And well, we understand what closed surfaces look like pretty well.
A closed surface which is connected is just determined by its genus, and so here are some examples.
So what happens when you evaluate Z on a sphere?
So let me draw that sphere this way. Well, to emphasize that it was a sphere, I drew a little
equator here, and that equator is giving you a recipe for cutting the sphere into two pieces.
And well, that decomposition tells you exactly what to do in order to extract this number.
Namely, the first piece, the half sphere that's on the left, is a bordism from the empty set to
the circle, and that corresponds to the identity element in A. And the second piece is what you
evaluate Z on in order to get the trace. So the complex number that you would get by evaluating
on the surface of d to 0 is just the trace of the element 1. So that's certainly a complex
number that you can extract whenever you have a commutative for baneous algebra.
You can evaluate Z on a surface of genus 1, on a torus, and well, I'll leave this to you as an
exercise. The complex number that you extract in that case is actually an integer. It's the dimension
of A as a vector space. And well, you can
try to play this game in general. I don't think you get something that has a name,
but it's certainly something which is an invariant of this for baneous algebra. So what happens if
you, for example, you wanted to evaluate this on a surface of genus 2, depicted like this?
Well, in order to figure out what complex number to associate to it, you would cut this circle
into pieces where you know what Z is supposed to be doing. So here I've drawn some circles that
you can cut along. And if you cut along these circles, you will cut this surface into, it looks
like, six pieces. Two of those pieces are disks, and four of them are pairs of paths. And so this,
you would get a complex number of pieces. So you would get a complex number of pieces. And
you would get a complex number that was obtained by composing some linear maps that you can
understand if you understand A as a for baneous algebra. So this is, well, let's say this is
something. This is a complex number. And the content of this folk theorem is essentially
that the complex number that you extract via this procedure doesn't depend on the particular way
these circles. So getting back to this point of view, let's say you imagine that first and
foremost, what you're interested in is the numbers that you get by evaluating Z on manifolds of
dimension D. So you have more structure than that. And what does that additional structure buy for
you? It buys a set of tools that you can use to compute those numbers. So here, if you wanted
to evaluate Z on the surface of genus G, well, you figure out what that is by cutting that surface
of genus G along a co-dimension one sub-metafold into pieces which are somehow easier to understand.
And then dimension two, that's a very powerful toolkit.
Because, first of all, if a manifold has dimension two, it's co-dimension one,
sub-manifolds have dimension one, so we understand exactly what they look like.
And a manifold with dimension two, you can really simplify it a lot by cutting it along circles.
Is it obvious that it doesn't depend on how you cut it on the circles and the definitions you gave?
What's that? The answer is not supposed to depend on-
The answer is not supposed to depend on- I understand that from the topological
theory point of view, this is clear, but does it follow from the list of axioms that Atiyah gave?
Yeah, yeah. I mean, the list of axioms that Atiyah gave said that Z of this picture, first of all,
is- it's one of the pieces of data that is in the definition of a TQFT, and the fact that it's given
by composing Z of the individual pieces is one of the axioms for how these invariants behave.
But maybe your question is really- you're wondering about the folk theory, like if I think-
I'm really wondering whether I cut it this way, or I can draw the surface in some other way,
and I cut it in some other way. Well, from Atiyah's definition, that's a requirement,
but the fact that you- just knowing- if you know what you want to assign to a pair of pants and a
disc, and you demand a couple of easy compatibilities between them, that that enforces all the other
compatibilities that might come from more complicated pictures, that's the content of that assertion.
Okay. Let me comment that it- a complete proof that if you start with a commutative
Frobenius, finite dimensional associative Frobenius algebra, that it doesn't depend
on the cutting has been- it is available. It's written out. It's on the archive.
Who should I attribute it to? Not the theorem, which was known to physicists for ages,
but the actual proof was given by myself, Greg Moore, and Graham Siegel in our paper in 2004.
We have an appendix, so we'll use Moore's theory and get a very careful proof of this.
All right, so you can think you're primarily interested in these numbers,
but the additional structure of this tensor functor is a toolkit for computing these numbers,
and in dimension two, it's a very effective toolkit because you can really simplify
two manifolds by cutting them into pieces. But for manifolds of high dimension, that's
really not true. A high dimensional manifold, first of all, co-dimension one sub-manifolds
can look very complicated, and if you're letting yourself only cut along closed sub-manifolds,
co-dimension one, then you can't necessarily simplify things very much. So
for this reason, various people have proposed enhancing a T as axi. To motivate this, maybe I
should just say one brief word about what's an example of how you could use
a T as axioms to compute one of these numbers. So let's say V is a closed manifold
of dimension D, and suppose that you cut it into two pieces, B minus and B plus, along some
co-dimension one sub-manifold M. So then Z of this B minus, well that's a B minus is a
bordism from the empty manifold to M. That gives you a linear map from the complex numbers into Z
of M, which you can just think of as an element in this vector space, Z of M. And similarly,
Z of B plus is something that you can think of as an element in the dual space of Z of M.
Similarly, Z of M with the opposite orientation. And then if you wanted to evaluate Z on the entire
manifold B, what you would get is you would just take this vector Z of B minus, which is in some
vector space, and this vector Z of B plus, which is in the dual space, and then pair them together
to get a complex number. So now let's suppose for simplicity that D is equal to three.
D equals three, and that we want to exploit this. We want to compute what Z does on manifolds
of dimension three by cutting them along surfaces. Well, the first thing that we need to understand
is what Z of M looks like, where M is now a closed manifold of dimension two.
And now what happens in a lot of interesting examples, including quantum trend Simon's theory,
is that there's a similar kind of formula for how you extract Z of M if you cut M into pieces.
So let's say now M is some surface of genus two, and I wanted to
sort of chop it into two pieces by cutting along some circle here. Let's say
in practice one can often associate
the circle, let's call it S, to S, some category Z of S.
And this S is here, it's cutting this two manifold into two pieces M minus and M plus,
and these pieces M minus and M plus determine objects of this category Z of S. Maybe Z of M
minus is an object of the category Z of S, and M plus maybe you should think of as an object in
the opposite category. It's kind of the same thing. And then such that the vector space that
the vector space that you're actually interested in, Z of M,
can be thought of as HOMS from Z of M minus to Z of M plus in this category Z of Z of S.
So this is analogous to what was happening up here, but it's one step more abstract.
Right here we were trying to compute a number by taking an element of
a vector space and an element of the dual vector space and combining them.
Here we're trying to compute a vector space by taking an object of a category and an object of
the opposite category and combining them using the structure of the category.
Could that be Z of M plus dual or Z of M plus bar with the opposite orientation?
Well, yeah, maybe.
Yeah, so the dimension of the overall manifold,
you're trying to apply this to the spatial manifolds.
So let's say D is equal to three. So to every surface, one of these gadgets
assigns a vector space. So it's not part of the T as axioms.
The T as axioms won't tell you anything about how to compute that vector space.
But in practice, you often have more than what was axiomatized by a T.
Yeah, I'm reluctant to interrupt, but I think if I explain what this means for
Turing-Simon's theory, this is this might understand you better.
Yeah, go for it.
I'll do that for a second. So first of all, in Turing-Simon's theory,
it's quite a gauge. And when you construct Z of M, M is a Riemann surface,
you impose the gauge theory constraint. So there are functions of the connection
that are gauging that. Now suppose you want to build M out of two pieces.
You can't completely impose the constraints on either side because then you won't be able
to reconstruct the whole answer by gluing them. Instead, what you do is for one piece,
you impose only the constraints by gauge transformations that are one on the boundary.
When you do that, you've got a vector space, but it's much, first of all, it's
infinite dimensional, Z of M for compact surfaces, finite dimensional.
It's an infinite dimensional vector space that has an action of loop group,
because you didn't divide by the gauge transformations that were non-trivial in the circle.
So for the complete M, you have this simple finite dimensional vector space.
But for the two pieces, you have infinite dimensional vector spaces,
each of which have an action of loop group. I think when Jacob says opposite category,
you can think of one as having level K and one level minus K.
And then when you glue them together, you can write the invariance.
And the invariance, I'm worried about that's actually a little bit correct,
maybe Jacob would criticize that, but roughly speaking,
the invariance are the finite dimensional vector space.
So just to say one more thing. So an object in the category in this case is not just a
vector space, but a vector space with the action of the loop group.
So from your point of view, Jacob, this category was completely
something else. It's a third thing. It's not related to the categories we were talking about
before. Well, let's say quantum turn assignment theory has this additional feature, which is not
encoded in Atiyah's axioms. And that additional feature is interesting. And maybe we could now
try to enhance Atiyah's axioms to encode that too. That's what I want to say next.
Maybe that's not your question.
Well, in Edward's explanation, this additional thing, which was this loop group in the middle,
well, it was somehow related to the topological field theory we had in the very beginning.
Here it looks like you're adding some other category.
Well, if you like, he's going to axiomatize the assumption that topological field theory
is always like turn assignment. For the example of turn assignment, I explained to you why this
structure exists. Maybe the term topological quantum theory is evoking for you something that
has more structure than Atiyah axiomatized. So if that explanation of what you were assigning the
circle sort of made sense as something that should be there, then Atiyah didn't include that. So
it needs to be.
It confuses me that the thing that you have in the circle is perhaps some additional perhaps
vector space or set of variables. Maybe call them edge models or something like this.
Category doesn't work.
You don't want to think of it as a category.
It's the set of highest weight representations of the current algebra. You could think of it that way,
the Z of S, at least the objects in Z of S.
There's a loop group. It has a Lie algebra, which is your current algebra of level K.
They have highest weight, they have unitary representations, highest weight representations.
Z of S, the objects in Z of S are the unitary representations of that loop group, of that current algebra.
Right, perhaps it would help me. So you have this category. What are the objects and morphisms of
this category? In the trans-Siemens theory example or in general? In the trans-Siemens
theory example. There's the category of positive energy representations of a loop.
You know, if you fix a particular level that you're interested in studying.
Well, there's a notion, in general, if representations of a group forms a category,
because if I have two representations, I can talk about a linear map between them that preserves the action of the group.
So, if I have two representations, I can talk about a linear map between them that preserves the action of the group.
The linear map is just going to be the vector. The co-bordism is a Riemann surface with some boundaries,
and the trans-Siemens level is considered positive when some negative on the others,
which you consider incoming or outgoing. And the vector space is getting the map, he said, from
the different lines between the different representations.
So, let me try to incorporate this into Atiyah's definition. So let me, I'll give something which is
a little bit informally. So, a once extended
is a rule. And now, at this time, let me start my rule at the top.
It assigns, it's a rule Z, which assigns to any closed D manifold. I'm going to call it M now,
violating my earlier convention. Any closed D manifold gets assigned a complex number.
Any closed D minus one manifold,
let's say, I'll also call it M, gets assigned D of M now complex vector space.
But now, what I associate to, let's say, the same manifold with the opposite orientation
is going to be the dual of that complex vector space. And what I assigned here, well,
is an additional structure that relates what happens at this level to what happens at this level,
at this level, that if, let's say, now if B is a D manifold with boundary,
then you can assign to it
vector that I'll write a Z of B, which lives inside
the complex vector space that you've associated to the boundary.
And now, there's a compatibility between the data that you see at these two levels and the data that
you see at this level, which is that if you're in a situation where you've, let's say, you have some
big manifold B, and you've cut it along a co-dimension one sub-manifold into two pieces,
B minus and B plus, well, then the invariant that you want to assign
to that big manifold of dimension D, that's a complex number,
you want that to be obtained by taking these vectors, Z of B minus and Z of B plus.
And these are elements, one of these is an element in Z of M, one of these is an element
in the dual space, and you pair them together. So far, this is the structure that you see
when you have a TQFT in the sense of a TIA.
But to say that it's extended, or once extended, is to say that you
also have data associated to manifold one dimension down. So if M is a closed manifold
of dimension D minus two,
and we're going to associate an object Z of M, and now this is going to be something,
every time the dimension goes down by one, the nature of the object that you're going to assign
gets a little bit more abstract. At the top level, you're assigning something very concrete,
namely a number. At the next level, you were assigning something a little more abstract,
a vector space. At this level, you'll assign something like a category. So Z of M is going to
be similar to your category. Maybe changing the orientation should essentially not change
that category, or maybe it should replace it by the opposite category or something like that.
And then if B is now a D minus one manifold with boundary,
and then you can associate to it an object, which I'll write as Z of B. This is now an object in the
category that you associate to the boundary of Z. And you have a compatibility similar to this,
of what's happening on this line and what's happening on line two. Namely, if now M is a
manifold of dimension D minus one, or sorry, if B is a manifold of dimension D minus one,
or sorry, if B is a manifold of dimension D minus one, and you've cut it into two pieces,
well then you should be able to compute Z of B, which is now a complex vector space,
by taking these objects, Z of B minus and Z of B plus,
and pairing them together somehow. And in this case, the somehow means you consider homs
between them in this category. And so I said this is an informal definition.
What is the monoidal structure on the categories? Are you taking...
I mean, there's a monoidal structure. If I think of this as a...
Maybe I should say here. Sorry, is your question, what replaces the fact that this is compatible
with tensor products at? Yeah, yeah. So what category can I get to a district union of M's?
Right. So let's say that the categories that you were interested in, you could write as the
category of representations of some finite dimensional algebra. Then what you would do
is tensor the algebras together. So there's an intrinsic way to describe this.
So in general, it's the deline tensor product of the categories?
Or it's... Well, I have to say exactly what kind of categories that I want to allow here.
If you're working, you might want to work with categories that you think of as sort of small
categories made of finite dimensional objects. In that case, you have this notion of the deline
tensor product that requires some assumptions in order to have it be defined. So you would
include those assumptions in the definition. You might interpret c linear category as
to mean something that could potentially be quite large, like the category of all complex
vector spaces, in which case there's a sort of companion tensor product. And so you might
take the deline tensor product, which can be defined in a lot more generality, with the caveat
that you might take the tensor products of things that have lots of finite looking objects inside
them and the tensor product category would no longer have that feature. But let's not dwell on
technicalities of exactly what I mean here, because the specifics of the definition are not going to...
The specifics of what the target of a TQFT is, is not really going to figure into the
the rest of what I'm going to say. How long do I have now? Oh, four minutes.
Well, let me say that this is an incomplete definition. So
there should be, or this should be supplemented.
By lots of additional gluing rules.
The gluing rules should tell you not just what happens when you glue together,
let's say, a closed manifold out of two pieces along a common boundary, but it should also
tell you what happens when you glue together a manifold of dimension D
as a union of pieces that are manifolds with corners.
And so in the non-extended case, we could summarize the TQ's definition not by writing out
exactly what the gluing rules were, but using the language of category theory,
we could say there is a bordism category and what a TQFT is, is a tensor functor from that
bordism category to the category of complex vector spaces. And there's something similar
that you can do here. So let me try to make this informal definition a little bit less informal.
And let me go back a little bit.
So remember, at the very beginning of this lecture, I introduced this category
Cob-D. This had as its objects all its manifolds of dimension D minus one.
So let me describe a variant or a generalization of this construction. So fix a closed D minus
two manifold X. Now let me find something. Let me call it Cob-D comma X. So this is going to be
defined like Cob-D and it's going to coincide with Cob-D when X is empty.
And so this is a category whose objects are D minus one manifolds
M with boundary X.
And what are the morphisms? Well, what we said in this case is that morphisms
from M to N are manifolds B, which are morphisms from M to N, meaning that the boundary of B
is identified with the disjoint union of M with N.
And here we're going to do the same kind of thing, but we don't take a disjoint union. So if M and N
are two manifolds that have a common boundary, then I can glue them together along their common
boundary to make a closed manifold. So morphisms from M to N are now D manifolds B where the
boundary of B is identified not with the disjoint union of M with N. And so this is going to be
is identified not with the disjoint union of M with N, but their union along X.
And now I want to observe that there's an additional structure here,
which is that, let's say, let me continue using X and Y. If X, Y, and Z are closed manifolds
of dimension D minus two,
and there's an operation that goes from Cob-D, let's say, X bar union Y to cross Cob-D
to cross Cob-D,
which is an object here is a bordism from X to Y, and an object here is a bordism from Y to Z.
And as before, we can glue these bordisms together to make a bordism from
from X to Z. So this is given on objects by the construction that takes a pair of bordisms
M and N and makes, let's say, M union along Y.
So there's some mathematical structure here, which is made out of manifolds of dimensions D,
D minus one, and D minus two, and it encodes the ability to both to sort of glue along
manifolds of dimension D minus two and manifolds of dimension D minus one.
And this sort of mathematical structure that you have obtained is something that has a name.
So this, this gives you, this gives an example of a C category.
Let me call this Cob plus 50.
The objects of this two category are closed manifolds of dimension D minus two.
And well, morphisms, what it means that this is a two category is that instead of having a
set of morphisms between two closed D manifolds or two objects, you have a category of morphisms.
So the morphisms from X to Y
is this category that I'm calling Cob D
that's union Y.
And so the reason that I'm saying this is because it's a convenient way to make precise
the definition that I was sketching very informally before.
Which is that definition a, let's say once extended
of dimension, again I'll say of dimension D. And now let me say with values.
In some
target category C, target two category, this just means
it's a tensor functor now not of categories but of two categories on this plus of D
to the category C. So here this C, what kind of gadget does it have to be? It has to be some two
category with a notion of tensor product. Let's say with a tensor structure.
Okay, so I've already gone over my time and I definitely did not reach my point.
But why don't I just pose by, I think you should go on for a little bit.
So C was not a, I expected C to be a category vector spaces.
It's going to be a two category, in order to be related to the definition that I gave earlier
this two category should have a feature that when I look at endomorphisms of the unit object
I should get the category of vector spaces. But you have some freedom as to what you can take
that two category to be. So a common choice is to take that two category to be something like
the objects to be something like C linear categories. And then you have the question
that was asked a while ago, what's the tensor product on those? And in good cases, there's
this deline tensor product on categories with good finiteness properties. And if you
if you don't want to assume, make a lot of assumptions, there's ways of getting around
needing to make them. So if D is equal to two, then tending to
comm plus D looks a little bit like you're introducing open, what physicists would call
open strings, right? The objects are points. The one intervals, those are the open strings.
And the endomorphisms are roll sheets. One of the big motivations for Mike Hopkins
and I when we started thinking about this was reading this paper of Kevin Costello about
sort of classifying these open closed theories and in dimension two.
So, okay, so this is the notion of once extended theory. And so what do you lose and gain by passing
from ordinary tqfts to these once extended tqfts? Well, the definition became a lot more
complicated, right? If the definition originally, if you write it down, category theoretically,
you need to know what a category is. And you need to know two examples of categories. You need to
know the category of manifolds and mortisms and the category of complex vector spaces.
But for this definition, you need to know not just what a category is, but what a two category is.
And you need to understand at least how to make manifolds into a two category. And also,
you have to decide where you want your field theory to land and understand
what the structure that you want to see over there is.
So you pay a cost in the level of abstraction that you're working at, but
pays a dividend, which is that in some sense, the theory becomes simpler. So
let's say a theorem, I think this is a recent theorem in full detail, but
let's say it essentially goes back to Reshetikin and Tariyev, is that
a once extended
tqft of dimension three,
the values in C linear categories properly interpreted
is the same data as a modular tensor category.
So in the early 90s, Reshetikin and Tariyev gave a recipe for starting with the data of
a modular tensor category, which is a particular structure that you expect to see
as the value on a circle of one of these theories. And they gave a recipe for starting with that data
and reconstructing three manifold invariants. And I think it wasn't until quite recently that this was
made precise in the language that I'm describing now, saying that there was actually a one-to-one
correspondence between the data of the modular tensor category and the data of a functor of two
categories in this sense.
I have one question. Semi-simplicity is not important for these statements, right?
It's important for the data of the modular tensor category and the data of a functor of two categories
in this sense.
Well, modular tensor category is a semi-simple category. And so
semi-simplicity is sort of not assumed, but in order to have one of these,
or let's say you don't input that the value on the circle is semi-simple, but it's something that
is forced on you by the axioms of one of these fully extended theories. It's analogous to what we saw
in Atiyah's definition. You could have made that definition without assuming that your
field theory, when evaluated on a D minus one manifold, was a finite dimensional manifold,
but the axioms actually forced that upon you.
So these sort of general themes is these axioms are not necessarily
going to force the values of your theory to have very strong finiteness properties.
Yeah, I have a question about that. This is something that I've always been rather confused
about. You can write out in it, going back to D equals two, where you have closed strings and
open strings, you can write out the axioms for the open closed topological field theory.
And I know that from your work, there's a proof that the Frobenius algebra, the commutative
Frobenius algebra, has to be semi-simple. But you can write down examples of open closed topological
field theories where the Frobenius algebra is not semi-simple. For example, if it's the
Durham cohomology of some compact manifold. So there seem to be two different kinds of open
closed topological field theories, at least in dimension two. And I don't see why that
shouldn't, why something like that can't extend to higher dimensions. So this is something I've
been confused about for a long time. So I don't know why you say that
something has to be semi-simple. Well, I mean, I thought that followed from your axioms. It
certainly proved in detail in papers like lecture notes by Pavel Sifronov, and I've discussed this
with him at length. And so from your formulation, there is definitely a statement that in D equals
two, the fully extended two dimensional TQFT. I think it has to do with whether or not you're
thinking of the values on points to be algebras or differential graded algebras. Like, certainly if
you allow differential graded algebras, there's lots of things with strong finiteness conditions
that don't make the algebras look semi-simple. Okay. In that case, the Frobenius algebra,
the circle would not be semi-simple. Right. Well, like, I mean, one example is
that you, like the Frobenius algebra that you assigned to the circle being.
That's what I'm asking about. I think Assan was, might've had that in the back of his mind
in the question he just asked. Right. So these examples that you're thinking about having to do
with the Romcom. One example that you can do is the B model. You can take your favorite smooth
projective algebraic variety, and then the category that you assign is really some kind
of derived category of coherent sheaves on that variety. And then that's a category that has the
kind of finiteness properties, assuming that the variety is smooth and proper to be able to build
one of these field theories. And when you evaluate on the circle, you get something that you should
really think of as a differential graded algebra rather than thinking about its homology.
And when you think of it as a differential graded algebra, it has some very strong
finiteness properties that are not necessarily visible at the level of its homology.
Sorry, I think I've, now I'm cutting into tea time, so I should probably stop.
That's probably a good stop here. Yeah. All right, let's thank, more questions for Jacob.
So the pair of paths picture you drew in two dimensions. If you think of the same picture in
three dimensions, and a once extended TQFD, is this, is the, so in two dimensions this gave you
the structure of algebra. So in three dimensions, this would give you the modular tensors, the
tensor structure on the category. So you're drawing with the usual pair of paths? Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. So that, that's what's responsible for the tensor product.
I just want to say a word about why it's a pity we interrupted Jacob so many times we didn't hear
that the next 10 minutes, because I think you probably would have told us about the next step
where you would have extended to a point. Yes. In the case of a three manifold. And that might have
been of interest to the audience because when you extended down to a circle, you had a loop group
representation. Now you're trying to, would then be trying to sort of, in some abstract sense,
factor it into two pieces. It's analogous to looking at the state of a quantum field on the
two sides of the local horizon. So what we didn't hear, because of interrupting Jacob a little bit
too much, would have been more analogous to a lot of the stuff that's discussed in the school
currently. Well, you wouldn't have heard about anything that's specific to that example, although
there is some work about that, that's quite recent. Well, we would have heard some kind of
abstract. You would have heard some abstraction of what you were looking for. What would accomplish
the goal of bringing it down to a point? Yes. Yeah. And maybe you could say a few words about that.
Why don't we take a one minute or, you know, a five minute break and, you know,
yeah, maybe we'll let people go. No judgment about who comes back and who doesn't.
Okay, let's move back a few minutes.
Uh-huh.
I once knew what that was.
I think I'm just like
but I'm not sure you get
I said, I don't know very well, but it's something that's
structured in elementary way, the homology of the surface, which I might do as a hypercalary
model. Should I say that again? There are two manifolds in the surface of the hypercalary model.
The answer to your question is associative. But yeah, unfortunately, for example, the hypercalary
surface, the low, the deep levels will be, so that's really wonderful.
We'll say simply connected through the, yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly.
It's three months on this first day. Number zero is it's
which is a fairly non-trivial, but the excitation, small excitation part of the
problems on the surface.
I was trying to wonder
extended thing is.
Once.
Yeah.
I don't know.
Even.
Even at his actions.
Was.
Explained.
To say.
Did not.
Explain how to satisfy.
I don't know.
What's been done.
There's.
Sure.
I'm sure.
There's.
Some papers by.
Roberts.
I think.
What.
In my understanding.
They constructed.
The category of blinds.
Which is what you would assign to.
Circle.
This.
For.
So they.
They constructed something.
Analogous to the.
Modular.
Category of.
Turn.
Signs.
When you start from.
So they may have.
Extended.
Yes.
And I mean.
The twice.
Extended.
Stuff is.
Is.
Kapustin.
Salina.
That's the two.
Category.
That's the fully extended version.
As far as I understand.
Okay.
It's probably not.
Been put in this.
Yes.
Right.
Yeah.
So there is.
Okay.
So let me.
Say a word about.
What would be the purpose of.
Is.
That.
You know.
Extended theory.
First of all.
It's a more complicated.
To define what it is.
And therefore.
It's maybe.
Harder to give.
It.
To define.
Is.
It's probably not.
Been put in this.
Yes.
Right.
So there is.
Okay.
So let me say a word about.
What would be the purpose of making this definition.
Is that.
You know.
Extended theory.
First of all.
It's a more complicated.
To define what it is.
And therefore.
It's probably not.
Harder to give it.
Find examples of them.
But.
It's easier to.
Sort of control.
The amount of data that you need to specify because of a statement like
this.
One of these once extended things,
at least when valued in C linear categories.
Is determined by the modular tensor category that you associate to the
three.
Manifolds.
You can try to write down examples of modular tensor categories that come
from purely algebraic constructions.
And then by this.
Russian.
Business.
You can then take something like that and couple it to this kind of
theorem and extract invariants of three.
Manifolds.
So.
The sense in which thinking about these extended.
And then thinking about.
Take you have to use in the sense of a TF.
In that they're.
Sort of determined by maybe a smaller amount of data.
Terminology.
Yes, here.
Something that is once extended.
Can be.
Extended.
To.
I've already been somewhat vague about exactly what the definitions are.
But.
Maybe a little.
Let me continue.
In that vein, a fully extended topological quantum field theory of
dimension D.
To be a similar data.
But now instead of a frontier between two categories.
Or ordinary categories.
It's going to be a frontier between D.
Let's say D is some.
C is some D category with a tensor structure.
Then you can consider.
A tensor filter.
From why don't I call this.
D fully extended.
From some D category,
which is defined entirely in terms of manifolds.
So let me just describe.
This very informally.
Cob D fully extended.
To some category where the objects are manifolds of dimension zero.
Morphisms.
Morphism between two objects is a bordism.
In particular, it's, it's a one.
One manifold with boundary.
Well, there's some notion of morphism between these things.
Which is if you have two, one manifold with a common boundary.
You can glue them together and then try to write that as the boundary.
So let me informally summarize that by saying, you know,
board isms between work.
So.
So these are certain kinds of two manifolds with boundary.
You want to think of them as having corners.
And so on.
And the D means we stop at dimension D.
So there's D morphisms, which are given by.
D manifold.
And saying that I'm viewing this as a D category means I'm keeping track.
Of a bunch of.
Data.
Which describes how such objects can be glued together to make other.
Objects.
And.
There's a philosophy.
Which was, I think, first proposed by.
Why hasn't Dolan.
Which is that this notion should be a very simple.
Theory.
Is what they call their.
Hypothesis.
And the informal statement of this.
Is that.
These fully extended theories.
Maybe I should say they're easy to classify.
And I want to just.
Very briefly.
Indicate why this is true.
In the one case.
You can actually think about without engaging.
With the theory of.
This notion of higher.
I want to do the example.
When D is equal to one.
Then fully extended.
Is the same thing as.
This definition.
Is equal to one involved zero manifolds and one manifolds.
Well, there's can't go any lower than zero.
And so.
This case in his paper and one paragraph.
And this remarks that, of course, this is.
Very easy.
And entirely trivial.
Let's just see why that is.
So.
All right.
One dimensional TQ of T in the sense of a T.
It's something that you need to be able to evaluate.
On manifolds of dimension zero.
To get a vector space.
Now.
My manifolds.
I said.
We're all going to be oriented.
So manifolds of dimension zero.
Are just.
Collections of points.
But orientations means I need to keep track of whether a point.
Has a positive orientation or negative.
So here's a picture of.
A typical manifold of dimension zero.
Well.
If I take Z.
Values in a positively oriented point.
That'll be some vector space V.
This determines what Z will do on a negatively oriented point.
Because of the lemma that I proved at the beginning.
Namely that when you reverse the orientation of a manifold.
You pass the dual space.
And then because this is supposed to be a tensor functor, that will tell you what Z has to do.
On this manifold here.
It needs to assign V tensor V star tensor V star.
Okay.
Well, we're not quite done because we have to say also what Z does on borders.
In other words, on manifolds with boundary.
But a manifold.
Since we're interested in tensor functors.
If we want to know what it does on a disconnected manifold with boundary.
That's determined by what it does on each of its connected pieces.
And well.
There's only a couple of things that one manifold with boundary can look like.
There's essentially five pictures that you could consider.
So you could consider.
Sort of.
Bordering from a positively oriented point to a positively oriented point.
With this 90 identity V.
Consider a bordering from a negatively oriented point to a negatively oriented point.
Which would be.
Identity on V star.
You could consider a bordism from a positively or.
Positive union negative to the empty set.
This would be assigned the evaluation.
From V tensor V star.
The complex numbers.
Or you can assign.
You could read that the other way.
Which case you'd assign.
The co-evaluation map.
Which lands in V tensor V star.
And the only really interesting case is what you assign to the circle.
That's a bordism from the empty set to the empty set.
Gets assigned a number.
But you can compute it like before.
By breaking the circle into a northern hemisphere and a southern hemisphere.
Or an eastern and a western in this picture.
And what you'll learn.
Is that the number that you get.
Is the one that you get by composing the evaluation with the co-evaluation.
And that's just the dimension.
And so what we see in this example.
Is that actually everything is determined once you move deep.
And so.
Let me turn that into.
So I'd like to ask a question.
So if we, if we consider.
The unoriented case.
Yeah.
Let me say that at the end.
That that's going to play into what I'm going to say next.
Let me give an incorrect formulation.
Of this biased.
So you can consider the collection of extended.
Totally extended.
TQFTs.
Valued in.
C.
And if you have such a TQFT.
Then what you can do.
Is just evaluate it on a point.
And then you'll extract an object.
Of whatever this.
Target category C is.
So roughly what they wanted to say.
Was that.
This was a bijection.
That if you have any object of C.
It completely determines.
This.
Fully extended TQFT.
So this is incorrect for two reasons.
And one of those is something that you can already see.
In dimension one.
So in dimension one.
If you're interested in TQFTs.
On the right hand side we're talking about vector spaces.
It's not true.
That every vector space can be.
Come from a TQFT in this sense.
A TQFT is determined by the vector space V.
But in order to have this co-evaluation map.
V has to be a finite dimensional vector space.
So.
What you actually learn.
Is that first of all.
If you look at the vector space map.
It behaves more like an injection.
And the things that it hits.
Well.
Let's say the image.
Is.
What we call the.
The collection of fully dualizable objects.
That's the image of the side of things.
What's that?
So in order for an object.
To be the evaluation on a point of a fully extended TQFT.
It has to satisfy a certain finiteness condition.
That in the world of vector spaces means finite dimensional.
But in a general end category with the tensor structure.
It's a.
Well.
It's a finiteness condition that we gave a name to.
And so the correct formulation.
Is that this.
This is true.
Provided.
That we.
We think about.
TQFTs.
Which are defined.
I said at the beginning.
There's several variants of the definition of TQFT.
Depending on how much structure you want to equip your manifolds.
You can think about.
You can think about unoriented manifolds or oriented manifolds.
Or spin manifolds or whatever.
And in this analysis.
We were assuming that manifold meant oriented manifold.
If we meant on oriented manifold,
then we wouldn't be able to distinguish between a positive and negatively
oriented point here.
And we would learn that we needed more data than just a vector space V.
We needed a vector space V that was identified with its dual.
And maybe the question was going to be.
Are you allowed any identification?
And no.
It has to be identified with its dual in a symmetric way.
It has to be identified with its dual via non-degenerate symmetric bilinear
form.
So in dimension one, if we were interested in unoriented theories.
This statement would not be quite right.
You would have to see.
Fully dualizable objects that had some kind of.
Additional symmetry.
And in higher dimensions.
Well, the statement is correct.
Provided that you think you think about manifolds equipped with the
maximal amount of structure that makes sense on a D dimensional manifold.
So TQFTs are defined on.
What I'll call D framed.
Manifolds.
And what I mean by that is that when I'm thinking about D manifolds.
They have to come with a trivialization of their tangent bundle.
And when I think about D minus one manifolds.
They have to have a trivialization, not of their tangent bundle,
but of their tangent bundle.
Plus a trivial bundle of rank one.
And so on for lower dimensional.
Okay. I think this is the end point that I wanted to reach and.
Why don't I stop here?
I can take questions again for five minutes and then I need to run.
Could you just draw some of the pictures that you would have to confront
a D equals two.
To.
Something that.
You mean.
So you would confront.
To set up a fully.
This maximally extended.
You know, you mean like what.
Insane that something is a fun.
Yeah.
So.
You would say something like this.
So anytime you have a manifold.
Dimension zero.
You have to assign an object of whatever your target category is.
And now.
Anytime you have a bordism.
So let's say we're valued in C linear category.
And you're going to have to assign a.
Or a.
Number of.
You're going to have to assign a.
So.
You would say something like this.
So anytime you have a manifold.
Dimension zero.
You have to assign an object of whatever your target category is.
And now.
So let's say we're valued in c linear categories. So a point gets assigned some c linear category
and then this gets assigned a tensor product of four different c linear categories. This gets
assigned a tensor product of two c linear categories and typically a bordism might look something like
like this and maybe it has some additional component and so every time I see a datum
like this I have to see a functor between those c linear categories and now there's two senses
in which this has to vary nicely. So one is that if I regard the endpoints as fixed there's a notion
of bordisms between bordisms. So every bordism is supposed to get assigned a functor but every
bordism between bordisms is supposed to give you a natural transformation between those functors
and those have to you know that has to be compatible with gluing
with gluing the bordisms with fixed endpoints. There's another structure so that's like
what they would call the the vertical structure of the two category
but there's another structure which is the horizontal structure which is I could consider also
so that had that the structure that I just mentioned it had only to do with functors between
two fixed c linear categories. I was never composing functors between c linear categories but now
oh let's draw it like this.
I also have the ability to compose these one-dimensional pictures. Each of these
one-dimensional pictures gets assigned a functor and when I stack them next to each other the
functors are supposed to compose and well everything is supposed to be true up to
isomorphism and the isomorphisms have to satisfy some coherence conditions but that's
that's the structure that one of these two it's the two manifold plays a role in the
previous thing you were talking about about the vertical structure the two manifold right
this horizontal structure mentions only one manifold although but there's a compatibility
between the horizontal structure and the vertical structure which is that the this is telling you
that you have some there's actually some category of bordisms which goes to some category of linear
functors and this composition is
so a point should go to an object in a two category right yes okay and so the morphism
between two points should be
it should be I mean I think a physicist would call if I understand well a physicist would call the
the morphism between the two points the open string state space
it should be a vector space right if I take if I take curly c to be the two category of
well maybe it's algebras by modules and by module morphisms
right so I mean a physicist would like to call the the the what you assign
your one morphisms between the zero morphisms is the open string state space
and then the the two morphisms will be just the the amplitudes from open and closed strings
in going and outgoing to open and closed strings and going
I can neither confirm nor do not
one final question so if I think of examples of categories let's say boundary conditions
there's a standard there's a canonical example of the Fukaya category so that's not a c linear
category but an a infinite category right so is there a way to that doesn't quite fit into the
axioms you right so I I stated this for n or d categories when you're interested in d-dimensional
tkfts but there's a an enhanced version and actually the the proof is by induction and
the induction needs the enhancement there's an enhancement where you know your your target is
really or let's say your domain is something that keeps track not just what what you if I had
continued I had some very rough definition of what the source category here is right it's like made
out of manifolds up to dimension d and what I would have said there is the d morphisms
you've specified some d minus one manifold which is has to do with what the source and target is
and then you want to write down d manifolds whose boundary is that d minus one manifold
and if I'd been careful I would have said the morphisms are diffeomorphism classes of those
objects but there's something fancier that you could do which is to think about the collection
of those things not the diff the set of diffeomorphism classes of manifolds with that
boundary but some kind of classifying space for all the compact manifolds having that boundary
right and then that's an object that forms an object that I would call an infinity d category
and it makes sense to talk about functors from that into a target which is an object of the same
nature and you have the same theorem there and the kind of thing that you're talking about is
the kind of thing where you you would need that level of generality because these a infinity
categories you know like a natural transformation between a infinity functors there's you shouldn't
really think there's a set of those you should think that there's a you know like a chain complex
of those there's
the sense in which these things form sort of non-trivial families parameterized by moduli
spaces of well I mean in the case of the Fukaya category this there's a two-dimensional tqft
associated to that and you see interesting invariants of like moduli spaces of curves
coming out of that story
I think we ate enough of jacob's time oh yeah